Chitralekha Gupta, Senior Research Fellow

CONTACT Information COM2-01-07, Augmented Human Lab, School of Computing, National University of Singapore Google Scholar, Website, Github E-mail: chitralekha@nus.edu.sg

RESEARCH INTERESTS My research interests lie at the intersection of deep learning, human-computer interaction, and audio, particularly in singing quality and lyrics analysis, controllability of audio generative models, explainability of AI, and audio-based assistive technologies.

Work Experience

Senior Research Fellow

Mar 2023 - Present

Augmented Human Lab, School of Computing, NUS

Research Fellow

Augmented Human Lab, School of Computing, NUS (PI: Suranga Nanayakkara) 2022-2023 Communications and New Media, Faculty of Arts, NUS (PI: Lonce Wyse) 2021-2022 Human Language Technology lab, Electrical and Comp Engg., NUS (PI: Haizhou Li) 2019-2021

Co-Founder of MuSigPro Pte. Ltd.

Aug 2019 - Present

A music technology start-up that commercializes two AI-based music technologies developed during my PhD and post-doc - a singing quality assessment algorithm, and an audio-to-lyrics time aligner.

Research Engineer at Airbus Defense and Space, Bangalore March 2013 - July 2014 Software Developer at Dell R&D, Bangalore Aug 2011 - Feb 2013

EDUCATION

Ph.D. at Dept. of Computer Science,

2015 - 2019

National University of Singapore (NUS)

Thesis: Comprehensive evaluation of singing quality; Advisors: Haizhou Li and Ye Wang

Master of Technology at Dept. of Electrical Engg.

Indian Institute of Technology Bombay (IIT-Bombay)

Thesis: Objective assessment of ornaments in Indian singing; Advisor: Preeti Rao

Bachelor of Engineering in Electronics Engg. M.S. University, Baroda, India

2004 - 2008

SELECTED PROJECTS

Through my experience as a research fellow and a senior research fellow, I have worked on a diverse range of projects related to audio and deep learning. A selected few of them are below:

- Music Analysis:
 - (a) Singing Quality Evaluation: I have worked on signal processing-based and machine learning-based explainable modeling of singing quality, based on pitch, rhythm, ornaments, and pronunciation.

12 papers published across ISMIR, Interspeech, APSIPA, IEEE/ACM TASLP 2017 - 2022

(b) Alignment and Recognition of Lyrics in Music: I have worked on kaldi-based modular ASR models for the task of lyrics-to-audio alignment and lyrics recognition. I have also co-authored works on espnet-based end-to-end ASR models lyrics recognition.

9 papers published across ICASSP, Interspeech, SMC, IEEE/ACM TASLP

2019 - 2022

- Controllability of Sound Synthesis using Generative Models: I have worked on exploring supervised and unsupervised methods of inducing control over certain attributes of synthesized audio by manipulating the latent space of Generative Adversarial Networks.

 6 papers published across ICASSP, ISMIR, ACM IUI, Springer, IEEE/ACM TASLP 2021 Present
- Assistive Augmentation Technologies:

I have worked with people with visual impairments to build an assistive tool that creates awareness of distant scenes through sonification, i.e. converting scene information into relevant sounds through generative models. *Published in ACM IMWUT*2023 - Present

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

- Chitralekha Gupta, Shreyas Sridhar, Denys Mattheis, Christophe Jouffrais, and Suranga Nanayakkara, Sonic Vista: Towards Creating Awareness of Distant Scenes through Sonification, IMWUT, 2024.
- Purnima Kamath, Chitralekha Gupta, Lonce Wyse, and Suranga Nanayakkara, Example-Based Framework for Perceptually Guided Audio Texture Generation, IEEE/ACM TASLP, 2024.
- Elliot Wen, Chitralekha Gupta, Prasanth Sasikumar, Mark Billinghurst, James Wilmott, Emily Skow, Arindam Dey, and Suranga Nanayakkara, VR.net: A Real-world Dataset for Virtual Reality Motion Sickness Research, IEEE VR, 2024 - Best Paper Award.
- Chitralekha Gupta, Purnima Kamath, Yize Wei, Zhuoyao Li, Suranga Nanayakkara, and Lonce Wyse, *Towards Controllable Audio Texture Morphing*, *ICASSP*, 2023.
- Xiaoxue Gao, Chitralekha Gupta, and Haizhou Li, PoLyScriber: Integrated Training of Extractor and Lyrics Transcriber for Polyphonic Music, IEEE/ACM TASLP, 2023.
- Chitralekha Gupta, Haizhou Li, and Masataka Goto, Deep Learning Approaches in Topics of Singing Information Processing (Overview Paper), IEEE/ACM TASLP, 2022.
- Chitralekha Gupta, Yize Wei, Purnima Kamath, Zhuoyao Li, and Lonce Wyse, *Parameter Sensitivity of Deep-Feature based Evaluation Metrics for Audio Textures, ISMIR*, 2022.
- Chitralekha Gupta, Emre Yılmaz, and Haizhou Li, Automatic Lyrics Alignment and Transcription in Polyphonic Music: Does Background Music Help?, ICASSP, 2020.
- Chitralekha Gupta, Haizhou Li, and Ye Wang, Automatic Leaderboard: Evaluation of Singing Quality without a Standard Reference, IEEE/ACM TASLP, 2019.

SELECTED ACHIEVEMENTS AND AWARDS

- DCASE Challenge 2023: Our generative model system for the Foley Sound Synthesis Task at this international challenge ranked 3rd amongst 26 submitted systems.
- MIREX 2020 and 2019: Our "Automatic Lyrics-to-Audio Alignment and Lyrics Transcription" system ranked 1st in the International Music Information Retrieval Evaluation eXchange platform for two consecutive years 2019 and 2020. (Press Release)
- NUS Graduate Research Innovation Program (GRIP) Award, July 2019, a start-up grant for MuSigPro Pte. Ltd.

PATENT (PENDING)

Chitralekha Gupta, Haizhou Li, and Ye Wang, "System and Method for Assessing Quality of A Singing Voice"; U.S. Patent Application No. 17/631,646 filed on 8 February 2022.

Grants

• Collaborator in MOE Tier 1/NUHS Seed Grant 2023, Topic: To assess the feasibility and objectivity of using an AI-based Speech Intelligibility Assessment Tool for people with Dysarthia to enhance the efficiency of dysarthria assessment and intervention in the local English-speaking population., SGD 138,000.

INVITED TALKS

- Invited talk at Meta ARIA Summit, Redmond WA, USA 2024.
- Invited talk at Music Research Symposium, Singapore 2023.
- Women in MIR panelist at ISMIR 2022.

Overseas/ Industry Collaborators

• CNRS, Toulouse, France (Dr. Christophe Jouffrais)

2023 - Present

• Meta Platforms Inc. (META)

2022 - Present

• AIST, Japan (Dr. Masataka Goto)

2021 - 2022

MENTORSHIP

- Mentored 2 PhD Students, and Co-supervised 2 Masters students.
- Served as a PhD Thesis Examiner of a student from Sorbonne University, Paris in 2023.